There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at how the brain’s
detox mechanism works—
the glymphatic system—
and more importantly,
what we can do to make
it work even better.
The glymphatic system is a newly
discovered drainage system
in the brain that clears the brain
of toxic waste byproducts.
Sleep is a great mystery.
A trait shared
across animal species,
sleep must be
of vital importance
to survive
natural selection pressures
to eliminate
such a vulnerable state.
Indeed, cringeworthy experiments
have shown
that keeping animals awake
long enough
can be fatal within
eleven to thirty-two days.
It turns out
sleep is of-the-brain,
by the brain,
and for the brain.
One function of sleep that has
been elucidated in recent years
is the clearance
of toxic waste byproducts
through a newly discovered
drainage system in the brain.
With the invention
of the encephalogram, EEG,
to measure brain wave activity,
the scientific world
was quickly disabused
of the notion that sleep was
a time of rest for the brain.
During certain stages of sleep
there is brain-wide activity
going on,
but what was
the brain actively doing?
More than 2,000 years ago,
Aristotle proposed that sleep
helps the body clean the blood.
Today, we know sleep may help
the body clean the brain.
Until 2012, we thought
that the brain was singular
among organs for recycling
nearly all of its own waste.
It had to,
since it was separated
from the rest of the body
by the blood-brain barrier.
But the barrier that keeps
toxins out of the brain
presumably keeps toxins in.
Then, in 2012,
a brain-wide
fluid transport network
was discovered,
termed the glymphatic system.
By microscopically tracking dye
injected into the brains
of mice,
scientists discovered
fluid-filled tunnels
surrounding blood vessels
in the brain.
The pressure wave
of arterial pulses
with every heartbeat
milks the fluid along
before eventually draining
into the cerebrospinal fluid
surrounding the brain.
What does this
have to do with sleep?
The whole system is only
really active when sleeping.
During wakefulness,
these tunnels are clamped down,
reducing glymphatic flow
by 90 percent.
The thought is the fluid shifts
might interfere
with targeted neurotransmitter
chemical communication
in the awake state.
So the biological need for sleep
may reflect the need
for the brain to enter
into a state to filter out
potentially neurotoxic waste
products like beta amyloid,
which is implicated
in Alzheimer's disease.
Perhaps this could help explain
why those who routinely get
fewer than seven hours of sleep
a night are at increased risk
of developing cognitive
disorders such as dementia.
Randomizing individuals
to have their sleep disrupted
by a series of beeps
administered through headphones
in a sleep lab
increases amyloid levels,
whereas improving sleep,
by treating sleep apnea patients
with CPAP, for example,
improves slow wave activity,
deep sleep, and appears
to lower amyloid levels.
PET scans show
even a single all-nighter
can cause
a significant increase
in accumulation of beta amyloid
in critical brain areas.
The problem is that
glymphatic brain filtration
appears to decline with aging.
Old mice only have
10 to 20 percent
the glymphatic function
of young mice.
This could be due
to a number of factors.
As we age,
we experience less
of the deep, slow wave sleep,
the type of sleep during
which brain waste clearance
appears to be the most active.
Further contributing
to the stagnancy,
our arteries tend
to stiffen as we age,
reducing the pulsations
that drive the glymphatic pump.
That also offers
one potential explanation
as to why hypertension
is tied to dementia.
The thickening of artery walls
with high blood pressure
also has a stiffening effect.
How can we counter this
age-related glymphatic decline
and keep our brains cleaner?
We'll explore
just that question, next.
What can we do to prevent the decline
in glymphatic brain filtration as we age?
Let’s find out.
Other than getting enough sleep,
what can we do to improve
the glymphatic clearance
of waste from our brains?
The provision
of a running wheel,
so mice could
voluntarily exercise,
has been shown to improve
glymphatic clearance
in aging mice,
which was accompanied
by a reduced buildup
of amyloid deposits
and improved cognition.
Sleeping position
may also make a difference.
Studies on rats show that
their natural sleeping position,
curled up on their sides,
allows for better
glymphatic transport
than sleeping on their backs
or stomachs.
People also tend
to spend most of their time
sleeping on their side,
particularly their right side
versus left,
compared to their backs
or stomachs.
This may maximize blood outflow
from the brain.
When we sleep
on our right side,
our right internal jugular vein,
the main blood vessel
in our neck
draining blood from the head,
is wide open,
and our left jugular
is partially collapsed
and vice versa.
Since most people have
a dominant right jugular vein,
sleeping on our right side
might maximize brain drainage.
Does it matter?
Well, people with
neurodegenerative disease,
mostly mild cognitive impairment
and Alzheimer's disease,
tend to sleep more
on their backs
than those
with normal cognition.
About seventy-two percent
spent at least two hours a night
on their backs compared
to 37 percent of those
with healthier brains,
raising
"the intriguing possibility
that head position
during sleep
could influence the clearing
of neurotoxic proteins
from the brain."
In crib death,
sudden infant death syndrome,
sleeping position
can be a life-saver,
leading to slogans like
"back to sleep,"
or more morbidly,
"face up to wake up."
It's premature
for an adult jingle,
maybe, on your flank
to not draw a blank?
The characteristic position
of poor sleepers
is on their back, though,
so maybe it's the poor sleeping
rather than the position,
per se,
that leads to cognitive decline,
or the causality
could be reversed,
with dementia deteriorating
good sleep habits.
Even if sleeping position
did matter,
it may take a night
in a sleep lab
to track your movements.
It turns out self-reported
sleep positions are often false.
Should brain benefits to side
sleeping ever be established,
you can train yourself with
so-called "positional therapies"
such as
the "tennis ball technique,"
which involves wearing a shirt
to bed backwards,
with a ball stuffed
in the chest pocket.
The uncertainties don't end
with sleeping position.
The glymphatic mechanism itself
was rapidly embraced
in scientific circles
and the popular press,
however,
it's been controversial.
It wasn't until 2019
that the first evidence
was published
that the glymphatic system
discovered in rodents
even existed in human brains.
Even the relationship between
sleep and Alzheimer's disease
is perhaps best summed up
in a recent neurology review
entitled "It's complicated."
Yes, those getting
less than 7 hours of sleep
may have higher rates
of Alzheimer's,
but those getting more than 8
are at higher risk too.
If anything,
population studies show
that longer sleep durations,
more than 8 or 9 hours,
are more strongly linked
to Alzheimer's disease
and dementia in general
than sleeping less than
5 or 6 hours.
The association between dementia
and long sleep duration
could be reverse causation,
where prodromal changes
in the brain
years before
Alzheimer's is diagnosed
causes prolonged sleep.
Long sleep duration may also
just be a confounding factor,
a marker of some
underlying health problem
that's the real culprit.
For example, oversleeping
may be a sign of depression,
which itself is an established
risk factor for dementia.
But there is a plausible
biological mechanism
for how extended sleep duration
could increase
dementia risk directly.
Longer sleep duration,
typically defined as sleeping
more than 8 hours a night,
is associated with signs
of systemic inflammation,
elevated levels of C-reactive
protein and Interleukin 6,
and both of those
inflammatory markers
in turn are associated with
an increase in dementia risk.
So much more
needs to be teased out
about the role
of the glymphatic system
before we make conscious efforts
to tweak it.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.